because this samsara is without a noble
beginning a first point is not discerned
of beings roaming and wandering on
obscured by ignorance and bound by
craving what do you think because which
is more
the water in the four great oceans or
the flow of the blood that you have shed
when your head was chopped off
while roaming and wandering on through
this long course
and then there were five venerables sir
as we understand the down the top by the
blessed one the flow of the blood that
we've shed when our head was chopped off
while roaming and wandering on
this alone is more than all the water in
the four great oceans
good good because it's good that you
understand my teaching in this way and
then he goes on
for a long time you've been cows and the
flow of blood you've shed when your head
was chopped onto the cow is more than
all the water in the four great oceans
and then for a long time you've been
Buffalo Rams goats sheeps chicken eggs
for a long time you've been Bandits
arrested for raiding Villages highway
robbery or adultery and the flow of
blood you've shed when you were beheaded
as a Bandits is more than all the water
in the four great oceans
so why is that this samsara is without a
noble beginning the first point is not
discerned of beings roaming and
wandering on obscured by ignorance and
bound by craving
this is enough to become
disillusioned or the translate
disenchanted or I think Ted up is kind
of dispassionate and liberated in regard
to all
sankaras all the terminations
so those Vehicles delighted in the
Blessed one's words and then it adds
while this teaching was being given the
minds of the Thirsty because from pava
were liberated from the phylum so they
became so
I suppose one sort of question is that
that might
it might not be immediately obvious why
I just reflecting on this point with
kind of be sufficient for somebody to like completely
like completely
free their mind from
craving entirely
yeah so the um
if you look at the nature of what was
described the nature of that samsara um
um
it's it's sort of um
it's kind of obvious that it boils down
to like just incessant repetition
just and even you could even get a
glimpse of that in this life
if you have to go through something over
and over again repeatedly
how disenchanting it becomes even stuff
that you actually voluntarily
engage with or want or even had the
desire for like saying like take take
the desire for some some Central
pleasure and repeat it long enough and
you will be sick of it
so nothing is actually changed
like it's still the same sense objects
still the same experience seems still
the same
pressure it exhibits still the same the
whole thing is same yet simply going
through it a few times you just you
can't have you you don't want it anymore um so
understanding or rather seeing then your
entire your entire existence everything
that you've ever been through everything
that you ever
would go through
uh
as just one of the
um
just one of the basically instances of
that endless repetition it gives this
thorough context of complete
disenchantment with anything that can
come your way good or bad doesn't matter
just you're just like it's not worth it
obviously that's in theory kind of can
be clear but you can then ask a question
so why then
isn't why then it was enough back then
to for those monks for that to be for
that that teaching for that comparison
to be enough for complete freedom from
passion and becoming our hands and today
is not enough to even become a sort of
partner for people even if they hear it
even if they understand it even if they
can see the point of it they're not free
even from the first three factors let
alone all the factors
so where's the difference
virtue yeah the level of virtue but the
virtue taken rightly
so they were all authenticity yeah yeah
difference you know the authenticity as
well um responsibility for one's mind States
um responsibility for one's mind States
actions choices which basically it was
more or less the norm back then it was
certainly more normal more average than
it is today
so today people will need to make a lot
of effort to just become like those
unenlightened protogenas of the olden
days of the Buddhist time
um so far from being more advanced we
are simply more proliferated more
drifted away
from certain basic phonological truths
so when those uh when those monks
although they were not free
when they heard this comparison when
they got the context that they realized
the depth of it
and their minds were freed there was
nothing that they wanted nothing that
they remained clinging to or adhering to
or assuming as theirs
because you can see that experience of
this is mine but this is mine this is
close to me how many times you've been
through that in this life
let alone if you expand that
infinitely in both directions
there's absolutely nothing no single
experience what
Desiring engaging
engaging
adhering to possession protecting
because that's also the thing see like
the things you have to protect God as
yours to maintain yourself
your possessions people your ownerships
things that are dear to you things that
offer you safety
you just need to how many times you've
been through that again one thing that's
kind of what I was thinking about in
regards to this was that
you know you can sort of see this
principle of repetition
on many different scales or in many
different ways like it kind of even in
terms of how um you know how people
sometimes speak about the world or
society and these kind of absolute terms
as though what's going on now where
something sort of a final importance or
as though there was some kind of
progress from the past oh now we live in
a great time of great turmoil and social
upheaval and whatever as though is that
is something new
um or like you know now there's great
progress being made in this direction or
that direction as though as though
there's some sort of like progression
through even history or whatever but if
you look you know there's never been a
time there's always going to be a war
there's always people being oppressed
there's always slavery of some kindness
always constantly constantly just repeating in
constantly constantly just repeating in
different versions of the same thing
and then you look okay what do I want to
do in my life you know what do I want to
kind of contribute to just generally as
a person asking a question what do I
want to actually yeah what should I do
where do I want to where do I want to
make an effort where do I want to make a
difference what do I want to contribute
to who can I help anybody and would my
effort go to waste because like if you
want to make a difference on just
and change one of the versions of of
events that are repeating throughout the
history and people's decisions and
everything else you realize well that
would be a wasted effort exactly
so how about I try and make the effort
where where things won't get repeated
and you see that the route yeah that's
the root of it all and you see like okay
like for that one the
how many times has your head been cut
off and look think about like all of the
and look think about like all of the
beings that are getting their head cut
their heads cut off in the world now
like and all of those people who are cutting
and all of those people who are cutting
off their heads are guaranteeing that
that same thing will continue repeating
again will they will get their heads cut
off and it's like those
you kind of see it as okay it's not just
kind of this thing that's outside that's
going on that I'm just sort of in I'm
the one perpetuating it I'm the one
doing this these beings are the ones
doing it
and what's the main reason for everybody
perpetuating is being part of it
and suffering the consequences what's
this soul
factor that unites them all what's the
root of it all basically
crazy more practically
more practically what's the reason for
killing stealing falling out fighting cheating
stealing falling out fighting cheating
lying essential desires
essential desires
desire desire basically it's root of all
the well inter what keeps it churning
if people say even if people were not
necessarily enlightened and free from
craving and understood for Noble Truth if people
and understood for Noble Truth if people
were free from desires there would be no
problems in the world
so desire is the reason people kill
animals kill each other so you can you
can you know you can prevent you can
conquer you can legislate you can shift
the culture
fundamentally you're just changing the
versions of it
you can fight the slavery you can change
the society but for as long as you
yourself are acting with the desire you
are contributing to the same repetition
of things not really going anywhere just
just changing its form but remaining the
same if you if you see the kind of the root
if you if you see the kind of the root
cause that it's desire is causing all
these problems then you you can see that
me giving food to all these people
changing the government and so on
are these people going to change their
desires are they going to no no so then
what is the point of me doing that you
know it can only help so much you can't
get so passionate about you know
change on that level because well
there's a thing like people get
passionate exactly and they realize you
realize that even if it's a change for a
for a better set of circumstances it's a
change that's uh that you're aiming for
it you're aiming it because you want to
fulfill your desire which means that is
the principle you follow that's the
principle that you're not uprooting so
when somebody else comes with a
different set of desires they will feel
equally justified in following their
principle of well but this is my desire
this is what I want and then you will
Clash sooner or later it has to happen
things cannot go smoothly because
everybody takes their desire and for
granted and feels Justified about it
and it was that if somebody if you can
show someone this is the problem
yeah if you if you can point out
that desire is the problem
you know how many people are willing to
give that up well exactly in order to
see the desire is a problem
you need to at least to some degree
start questioning your own desires even
if they seem good
and that's the thing that's why it's
like like a blindness Intoxicated by
centrality means you don't see the
problem of your desires
um fundamentally you don't see a problem
of of having any desires you might
thought this desire is a problem but
this other one isn't this is a good
desire but fundamentally you need to
start questioning him in that and
recognize well desire in itself
simply by having the nature of
pressuring me being under its influence
losing perspective on account of it not
being able to remain
unmoved by the by the force of Desire by
always having to like suffer on account
of saying no to it suffer if I don't get
enough of it and all of that
it should be seen as a problem but that
requires a reflection so that's why if
somebody is not even willing to think
that way you telling them the root of
all of the problems is a desire not the
state of the world they're not going to
hear that because their desire will say
no you're wrong because that's not what
I want
yeah but that's that's what the Buddha
said like himself that the mothers fight
with fathers with sons with daughters
Kings with Kings and everybody based on
account of centrality taking abroad
sticks beating each other killing
killing others harming others just it's
all because sooner or later those
desires will be coming from different
directions with different names
and and we kind of have what we want
or sometimes people want what we have
or what we want somebody else doesn't
want that
so they have a desire against it
so again it's it's going to be you know
the the famous Simulator for the mango
tree you climb up to to eat the mangoes at
you climb up to to eat the mangoes at
the top but somebody who can't climb the
tree but wants the mangoes he'll find
his means of getting them by cutting the
tree and and then getting the mangoes from
and and then getting the mangoes from
the ground while you're still in the
tree so that's the thing like you're
committed to certain ways because of
your desires but somebody else comes
sort of perpendicular to that with their
own set of desires and ways and you're
just in the way or or certain parts of
your life are in his way and that's it
that's all it takes
how many people are the desires are the
same everyone wants the same thing
okay maybe we can all just have to want
the same thing yeah that's impossible
that's like like let's let's let's all
animations there will be like thousand
people throwing a dice and every single
one of them getting the same number on a
dice you can imagine it
but practically that is absolutely
completely impossible it cannot occur
you can say probably that what's uniting
is that everyone wants to have pleasure
yeah but that's the same way dividing
things exactly it's like oh but what
makes what what what's Pleasant for me
it's not pleasant for you and that's
already that's always going to be a
conflict there if we come into each
other's way
yeah so so in order to understand desire is
so so in order to understand desire is
the problem as the as the as the fuel
for this whole samsara and
Perpetual kind of repetition of of
everything and nothing really you need
to have already had this woman have to
have some authenticity and recognize
that it doesn't matter if your desire is
good or bad on the surface presence of
Desire is bad
it's unbeneficial for you for others for
both that's where the the word said that the
that's where the the word said that the
arhan practices for the welfare of
others not by going and feeding them or
as I said like changing the society by
removing the desire in his experience
completely uprooting it
that is beneficial for him beneficial
for everybody that interacts with him
there will be there will be no
conflict of interest or whatsoever
because he has no interest left
um and plus of course he's able to you
know he would have understood it and
he's able to convey to somebody else
they want to hear it so Factory by
approaching the desire in your own
experience you are making samsara a
better place to that for one being less
basically one being less affected by desire it's
one being less affected by desire it's
factually better that is because that's
the level that matters that's the level
of samsara's fuel to put it that way
even if so miraculously I don't know
there's a king and he changes
the culture of his country and gets
everybody on the same page about
everything and everybody wants the same
thing again fantasy utopian idea but say
abstractly imagine it as something still
there's no difference in samsara
there is no difference because everybody
is still Bound by the same fuel Bound by
the same thread threaded Central desire
because as like you have to want the
thing that's actually going to bring
everyone together which is non-design
you know non-delight in the world
desire for sensuality so it's like you
have to want the same thing which
if everyone wants the same thing it has
to be the thing which unites everyone
right right that makes everyone our
hands which and and what what cannot be
true what cannot ever unite everyone is
the objects of their sense desires
because that's that's the variety of
sense objects is the the kind of what
inside the desire
and see as we said as we started this
even if you have a desire to a certain
sense objects repeat it few times and
you will lose the desire for it you'll
in other words you'll move on to
something else you're not going to
approve the desire it's just desirable
move on to something else so even within
yourself it's impossible to always want
the same object of your desire let alone
now when you introduce thousands more
beings animated inconceivable that's
what I mean like when you yourself
cannot sustain desire for one object
just equally with the same degree
impossible because it's not in your
control to begin with so yes exactly
then you recognize well everybody has a
desire so if everybody would want to be
free from desire that could be a common
value but again that would come out of a
desire at the time and as such
impossible for everybody to want to be
free from these eyes that's able to say
there are four types of people some some
don't even need to hear the teaching
they'll figure where the problem is and
freed himself but then on the other end
of that Spectrum you have those that the
Buddha himself can be teaching and it's
like flogging the dead horse it will
make no difference whatsoever they will
not hear it or want to hear it or want
to make the effort because if you did
you would more often than not you would
wish to not have designed at all because
see I have this Prussian desire I have
to go and work and earn and fight for
things that I want and protect them and
you might do it once twice but it's
exhausting it's tiring would it be nice
if I could just be left at peace and not
even have this pressure that's forcing
me to act and so on sleep slave turn on
designs but even being able to recognize
what you just described that's the
beginning of understanding of the of
your situation yeah but if it does like
that's exactly the thing it's
on that level you can see internally the
same again how you're just defeating you
know trying to solve the problem let me
just kind of do this work and find okay
I have to do it but kind of you know
even as you're doing it that's all
you're doing is perpetuating exactly the
same thing kind of reminded me of that
um what you were saying the other day as
well about the death like using just
getting another oh yeah borrowing from
here to pay back there and literally all
you're doing is perpetuating the state
of death different versions different
kinds of deaths from different people
but it's the same still under the same
thing exactly again and again and like
you know every time you act out of
Desire it's that it doesn't matter even
how coarse or how subtle it's that exact
same thing you're just perpetuating the
same thing
so it's and that's samsara in itself as
well become fed up really of that it's
not
that's why you can become free free over
here and now even you know you don't
necessarily need to remember all of the
past lives or anything it's just that
nature of repeasing the same thing
in different versions
and but it kind of boils down to that basic
but it kind of boils down to that basic
essential desire manifests itself it's
unpleasant in its core you feel the pain
you don't want to deal with it there and
then so you act out to relieve the pain
knowing it will come back because you
didn't really address it so you're just
procrastinating postponing delaying
putting it off
um
and becoming completely hooked and
addicted to that the distraction that
comes out of that mode of being
yeah but even then and then even there and
but even then and then even there and
then you could and deep down you know
that the only reason you you won't send
subjects of pleasure is because it's
painful to not go for them
so not having them it's painful and
that's why you act out because you you
don't want to deal with the pain
just like any addiction exactly the same
you know you can even know how harmful
it is you know everything is falling
apart as a result of it but still when
that pain touches you you choose to turn
a blind eye and and go for the
distraction instead of instead of
addressing it instead of being able to
well to say no to it and you know as
well that's the other difference I think
it makes in
um
just having this perspective of some of
samsara generally
it's the same thing it's like when
you're an addict you kind of are aware
that the pressure of the addiction that
you feel now is nothing other than the
results of you having having given
giving it into it and again and again
and again like that's literally your
inheritance so if you then don't give in
you know for a period of time you know
that the pressure will have to last
exactly and that's the difference it makes I
and that's the difference it makes I
think when you you know realize okay
this entire situation that I'm in or any
kind of suffering I could experience or
any suffering that any being is
experiencing is is his inheritance in fundamentally
is is his inheritance in fundamentally
yeah so
I'm I've inherited this situation
of pain of suffering and all what I need
to do is stop fueling it stop adding to
it
inherited that from yourself
from yourself
there's no first point before which you
were that less and then you incurred it
but yeah
inheritance plus taxes
always yeah yeah it's kind of it's
the the interest rate is growing yes
yeah it's not it's not a static thing
yeah either you're paying it off or
throwing it more yeah